<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and full account of a conference held about religion, between Dr. Tenison and A. Pulton one of the masters in the Savoy Published by authority.</title>
            <title>True and full account of a conference held about religion, between Dr. Tho. Tenison and A. Pulton one of the masters in the Savoy.</title>
            <author>Pulton, A. (Andrew), 1654-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4209A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29726</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70878)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29726)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2038:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and full account of a conference held about religion, between Dr. Tenison and A. Pulton one of the masters in the Savoy Published by authority.</title>
                  <title>True and full account of a conference held about religion, between Dr. Tho. Tenison and A. Pulton one of the masters in the Savoy.</title>
                  <author>Pulton, A. (Andrew), 1654-1710.</author>
                  <author>Tenison, Thomas, 1636-1715. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Nathaniel Thompson at the entrance into Old-Spring-Garden near Charing-Cross,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The version as given by Pulton.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: A true and full relation of the late conference between Dr. T. &amp; A.P. one of the masters of the Savoy.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of the edition with "Dr. Tho. Tenison" in title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29726:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29726:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True and Full ACCOUNT OF A CONFERENCE HELD ABOUT RELIGION, BETWEEN Dr. Teniſon AND A. PULTON One of the MASTERS in the SAVOY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Published by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nathaniel Thompſon</hi> at the Entrance into <hi>Old-Spring-Garden</hi> near <hi>Charing-Croſs</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:29726:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A. P.</hi> having been Eighteen years out of his own Country, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not yet to any Perfection of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Expreſſion or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography, wherefore for the future he will crave the favour of treating with the <hi>Dr.</hi> in <hi>Latine,</hi> ſince the <hi>Dr.</hi> finds fault with his <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29726:2"/>
            <head>To the Indifferent READER.</head>
            <p>IT was wholly beyond <hi>A P</hi>'s. deſign, when he was invited to the Conference, (now ſo much noiſed through the Kingdom) to proceed ſo far as to Print; but as he went to it, as to a private meeting, ſo he never intended (being returned home) to make any noiſe of it, more than by giving by word of mouth, a ſimple account of the whole matter, to ſuch as might privately deſire to know the ſubject, and ſucceſs thereof. But being alarm'd all <hi>Friday, Saturday<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Sunday</hi> morning, with reiterated reports of his being run down, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced with five, eight, fifteen of his fellow Jeſuits, and of the Doctors putting many Queſtions to him, without being able to obtain any Anſwer; at the inſtance of many <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> who had been derided by the Dr's Party, as though their cauſe had been totally loſt: <hi>A. P.</hi> thought himſelf obliged, after his publick exerciſe of <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Afternoon, to ſpeak to his Auditours as followeth; <hi>There having been many falſe and ſcandalous reports of a late Conference, I conceive many
<pb facs="tcp:29726:3"/> here preſent may be in expectation, of having now ſome account thereof; but it is not our cuſtom to give occaſion of offence by Pulpit clamours, and making private Affairs publick: And being not yet informed that the Doctor has begun, or countenanced theſe reports, I ſhall omit at preſent to ſay any thing relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; though, if juſtly provoked, the</hi> Sunday <hi>following, I ſhall give a ſincere full, and modeſt account of the whole.</hi> The Doctor having heard of this, was pleaſed on <hi>Munday</hi> in the evening, in company of Dr. <hi>Cla.</hi> to give <hi>A. P.</hi> the honour of a viſit in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and to uſe his own terms, to <hi>expoſtulate with him,</hi> concerning the unbeſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of making ſuch Conferences, the ſubject of a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit diſcourſe; adding, that he not having taken thoſe meaſures, it ſeemed reaſonable <hi>A. P.</hi> ſhould ſpeak of it in that nature, <hi>A. P.</hi> replied he was content, but that ſome means ſhould be uſed to diſabuſe the deceived multitude; to which the <hi>Dr.</hi> anſwered, he was willing to proſecute the Queſtion propoſed, by writing, and that he would Anſwer the difficulty out of St. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> But <hi>A. P.</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that that was the leaſt part of his proof, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the <hi>Dr</hi> would allow that he might produce all thoſe Teſtimonies which he would have alledged in in the Conference it ſelf, had not the <hi>Dr.</hi> refuſed to hear them; and that then the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſhould give his
<pb facs="tcp:29726:3"/> Anſwer. But the <hi>Dr.</hi> deſiring he might Anſwer that of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> firſt, <hi>A. P.</hi> aſſented, and both ſides agreed, that the firſt Copy ſhould be mutually ſent to the oppoſite Party. (Here the <hi>Reader</hi> is deſired to note, that this was the only Agreement made between the Parties in the <hi>Savoy</hi>) and there was no farther challenge on either ſide, much leſs, did the <hi>Dr.</hi> come to ask Pardon, as ſome are ſaid to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported. Now here was no mention made of giving, or not giving in writing, a publick account of the meer matter of fact paſt, but only of going on with the points then in debate; and therefore if the <hi>Dr.</hi> charge <hi>A. P.</hi> with not ſtanding to his agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as he ſeems by his Letters to threaten) it will be without ground.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>A. P.</hi> ſeeing the falſe and injurious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports daily increaſe, and that the <hi>Dr</hi>'s. Party ſpread them by written Copies, in Coffee-houſes, thought himſelf obliged in juſtice to the Truth, to write ſome ſhort account of the matter of Fact; the firſt Copy whereof, he ſent to the <hi>Dr.</hi> the <hi>Friday</hi> following, and then gave ſome few to his friends, ſo to ſtop the Torrent of the falſe and ſcandalous reports which ran about the whole City, and great part of the Nation. The <hi>Dr.</hi> ſeemed to take this ill, though without any grounds; he having then compleated a Narrative of ſeven or eight ſheets. And whereas he ſays in his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:29726:4"/> Copy, that he and <hi>A. P.</hi> had agreed of <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Method of ſetting forth the matter at large,</hi> it is far from true, there never having been a word mentioned of it. <hi>A. P.</hi> ſo far as by-hours from greater Employments ſhall allow, will ſhew that it is the <hi>Dr.</hi> who in his <hi>Narrative</hi> has truly inverted the whole Order of the Conference, and ſlightly paſſing over the chief ſtreſs of <hi>A. P</hi>'s. Arguments, and moſt material Inſtances, has taken pains to Illuſtrate his own Anſwers to certain by-queſtions, purpoſely thrown in by him to amuſe the Auditours, and divert their attention from the chief Argument, and take occaſion thence to tax <hi>A. P.</hi> with not anſwering his Queſtions. It is deſired, that every one will be ſo favourable to truth and equity, as to ſuſpend his judgement, till ſuch time as they ſhall have read <hi>A. P</hi>'s. Remarks on the <hi>Drs. Narrative;</hi> by which he will evidence to the World his many miſtakes, miſreprenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, want of ſincerity, and his artifice, in confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wholematter of fact; and that neither in his Narrative, or Conference, (though much unlike) he has given any ſatisfactory Anſwer to the main Queſtion, nor gained any point againſt the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> unleſs <hi>A. P</hi>'s. not calling to mind <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>III</hi>'s. Name, or a Verſe of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> be a total overthrow of the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Cauſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29726:4"/>
            <head>A True and Full RELATION Of the late CONFERENCE BETWEEN Dr. T. &amp; A. P. One of the MASTERS OF THE SAVOY.</head>
            <p n="1">1. ON <hi>Monday</hi> the 26th. of <hi>September,</hi> there came a Youth to <hi>A. P.</hi> who deſired to know, if he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to accept a Conference with Dr. <hi>H.</hi> He anſwer'd, he was; but on <hi>Tueſday</hi> it was told him, Dr. <hi>T.</hi> was the Perſon he muſt engage with, at Three in the Afternoon on <hi>Thurſday</hi> follownig.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29726:5"/>2. <hi>On</hi> Thurſday, <hi>as was appointed, the Parties met,</hi> A. P. <hi>cume with one Witneſs, (no Prieſt,) the</hi> Dr. <hi>alone, who complaining that</hi> A. P. <hi>came with Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, whereas, he had no body in his Company;</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> he thought it reaſonable, that ſome one ſhould be preſent, that might be witneſs of all ſhould be ſaid or done on either ſide; But if the <hi>Dr.</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved not thereof, he was content, <hi>the Chamber (which now was almost full of People) ſhould be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that the</hi> Dr. <hi>with the Youth upon whoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they met, ſhould remain alone with</hi> A. P. <hi>But the</hi> Dr. <hi>deſiring the Man of the Houſe might alſo be preſent,</hi> A.P. <hi>aſſented thereto, upon condition he might alſo be allow'd likewiſe to have one Witneſs, to wit, Mr.</hi> M. <hi>the</hi> Dr. <hi>excepted againſt that Gentleman, and had a private debate with him; Whereupon</hi> A. P. <hi>was content that Gentleman ſhould retire, and pitch'd upon another who caſually came in, tho' not known by name to</hi> A. P.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſitting down, invited</hi> A. P. <hi>alſo to place himſelf by him, which he did; but</hi> deſired very much, that Pen, Ink and Paper might be brought, and every thing writ down which ſhould be ſaid on either ſide; <hi>but this was not accepted of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Youth appearing (for whoſe ſake the</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference <hi>was</hi>) A. P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> That having of late in his Catechiſms ſhew'd the neceſſity of true Faith for Salvation, and of ſome aſſur'd means to find out the ſaid true Faith, which he had ſhewn to be a True and Infallible Church; This Youth had been mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to entertain thoughts of joyning himſelf to the Roman Catholick Church; <hi>he deſired therefore,</hi> that the <hi>Dr.</hi> (if he could) would be pleas'd to aſſign a better Rule of Faith, and which might
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29726:5"/> ſerve to keep the Youth in the Perſuaſion he had been bred in: The <hi>Dr.</hi> reply'd, <hi>That the Boy had told him no ſuch thing, but that</hi> A. P. <hi>had told him of the contradictions of</hi> Luther; <hi>and when the</hi> Dr. <hi>asked him, what Book of</hi> Luther <hi>it was, the Youth anſwer'd,</hi> a Book in Quarto; whereupon the <hi>Dr.</hi> told him, <hi>That</hi> Luthers <hi>Works were not in that Volume, but in Folio.</hi> A. P. <hi>granted</hi> he had ſpoke to that purpoſe of <hi>Luther,</hi> and had ſhewn that <hi>Luther</hi> had taught now Seven, then Three, then Two, and at laſt only One <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and there being conſequently no Unity in his Doctrine, he had no Spirit of Truth in him: <hi>But he ſaid,</hi> he never had brought any Book to the Pulpit with him; Then the <hi>Dr.</hi> reply'd, <hi>The Boy began with a Lye, to which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That did not follow, for he had ſhew'd him ſuch a Book in his Chamber, which was not any piece of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's</hi> Works, but had Quotations out of them: <hi>At which the</hi> Dr. <hi>had a fling at Equivocation, ſaying,</hi> That <hi>A. P.</hi> had ſhew'd him no Book, <hi>to wit,</hi> in the Pulpit, but he had in his Chamber, to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of <hi>Luther;</hi> he <hi>ſaid</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> depended not upon <hi>Luther,</hi> and that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church had not always taught Seven Sacraments; <hi>to which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That the Church then defin'd the preciſe number of Sacraments, when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate began concerning the Nature and Eſſence of a Sacrament, but had never taught and declared a contrary number: <hi>Here</hi> A. P. <hi>to avoid wandering, preſs'd the</hi> Dr. to aſſign his Rule of Faith.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He having aſſigned the Holy Scriptures,</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> There were two things incumbent on the <hi>Dr.</hi> to prove. 1. That the Volumes he call'd Holy Scripture, were truly ſuch. 2. That when ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29726:6"/> prov'd, they were a ſufficient Rule by themſelves of Faith. <hi>But to the Second Point nothing was ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>To the Firſt the</hi> Dr. <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> they had been handed down from the Apoſtles. <hi>A. P.</hi> deſired the favour <hi>to know, by what hands? The</hi> Dr. <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> The Scriptures were prov'd by the Teſtimony of <hi>Turks, Jews, Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and that he had the ſame certainty for them, as for there having been ſuch a Man as <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Caeſar. Here Mr.</hi> M. <hi>asked the</hi> Dr. <hi>(who then turning towards him, ſeem'd to ſpeak to him)</hi> whether <hi>Turks, Jews,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi> made up part of the Teſtimony he alleag'd for Holy Writ? <hi>But</hi> A. P. <hi>deſiring that no body ſhould argue but himſelf, deſired to know further of the</hi> Dr. from what immediate hands the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had receiv'd their Bible, when ſhe began the Reformation? <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> from the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, and that he meant by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church,</hi> all thoſe different Bodies which make up the number of Chriſtians. <hi>Then</hi> A. P. <hi>urged to know,</hi> whether all thoſe different Parts made one True and Uncorrupted Body, or whether at leaſt there was then any ſuch thing, as a True and Uncorrupt Part at leaſt of the Whole; <hi>But the</hi> Dr. <hi>would not allow the Whole to be ſo, nor yet aſſign any Part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of void of much Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Here a pleaſant School-Maſter perceiving the Argument to pinch, with wry Mouths and antick Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, offer'd to</hi> A. P. <hi>a Picture (as he ſaid) of the</hi> Bleſſed Trinity: <hi>A. P.</hi> perceiving that the ſtanders by were diſpoſed to Laughter, <hi>reply'd,</hi> That God having been pleas'd to appear to the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> under the form of an Antient Man, he ſaw no reaſon why he might not be Painted as he appeared,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29726:6"/> provided one meant not to delineate him in his own Nature; <hi>Which ſaid, he return'd to his Argument, and preſs'd much to know how the</hi> Scripture, having been deliver'd unto them by corrupted, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently falſe Witneſſes, could be held for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and undoubted Word of God. <hi>But the School-Maſter continuing to throw in impertinent Queſtions, with many ridiculous geſtures,</hi> A. P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> he came not to argue with a Buffoon but a Dr. <hi>This was ill taken, and the</hi> Dr. <hi>was pleas'd to read a Leſſon of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon that Subject, and went about to prove, that</hi> A. P. <hi>had violated the</hi> Holy-day: <hi>And when Mr.</hi> M. <hi>ſaid in</hi> A. P's. <hi>defence,</hi> That St. <hi>Paul</hi> had us'd as ſharp Language on a like occaſion, <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>reply'd,</hi> were he St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he might do ſo too.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Here</hi> A. P. <hi>perceiving the</hi> Dr. <hi>willing to enter a Diſcourſe of a different Subject,</hi> he wiſh'd Mr. <hi>M.</hi> to withdraw to the Window, that the <hi>Dr.</hi> might have no occaſion of diverting the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or complaining, there were two againſt one; <hi>which done, he urged a great while the</hi> Dr. <hi>to declare,</hi> How he was aſſured of his <hi>Bibles</hi> being the True and Uncorrupted Word of God, ſince he believ'd all thoſe who had delivered it, were Superſtitious and Idolatrous, or (at leaſt) Falſe and Corrupted: And how, ſince he taught they had Corrupted and depraved the Senſe of Holy Scripture, he could believe upon their Authority, the Letter to remain Pure and not Corrupted, <hi>uſing thereto this Simile,</hi> That if one ſhould bring a Deed into a Court of Juſtice, atteſted only by Lyars and Corrupted Witneſſes, although never ſo many, it would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make good any Action in Law, or find Credit with any not Corrupted Judge; <hi>preſſing this with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29726:7"/> much earneſtneſs, the</hi> School-Maſter <hi>return'd to his former humours, putting in impertinent Queſtions, and ſaying,</hi> the Buffoon asks this. <hi>But</hi> A. P. <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting his impertinences, preſs'd the</hi> Dr. <hi>continually for a poſitive</hi> Anſwer, <hi>and the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſaid at laſt,</hi> There were True Chriſtians of an Uncorrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine at ſuch time as the Reformation began, <hi>A. P. preſs'd to know,</hi> whether they were viſible or invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, at that time? If inviſible, he deſired to be ſatisfy'd, how they had taken the <hi>Bible</hi> from inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hands? If viſible, where they were? in what Place or Country? <hi>But to this never could obtain any ſatisfactory Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>During two hours and a half, which this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate laſted, all their Anſwers were as follows. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the</hi> D. <hi>appeal'd to the</hi> Greek-Church, <hi>to which</hi> A: P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> That he had not then received the Scripture from the Univerſal, but a Particular Church, <hi>and deſired to know,</hi> if the <hi>Dr.</hi> would ſtand to that Plea, and be Judged by the <hi>Greeks: If ſo,</hi> A. P. <hi>would demonſtrate to him,</hi> That all the Opinions, or at leaſt the Chief wherein the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> Diſſents from the <hi>Roman Catholick Church,</hi> were Condemn'd and Anathematiz'd by Two Great Councels called in the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> on thoſe Subjects ſince the pretended Reformation. <hi>Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſaid,</hi> the <hi>Greek-Church</hi> had been Corrupted by our Miſſions, <hi>which is far from being ſo, they having been of the ſame Judgement many Hundred Years ago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Then he Appeal'd to the</hi> Bohemians; A. P. <hi>asked,</hi> Whether he would be Judged by them? If ſo, he wou'd find, how, although agreeing in ſome Points not material, yet in the Subſtance they much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29726:7"/> Diſſented from the late Reformers, who deſcended not at all from them, no more than they from the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>againſt</hi> A. P's. <hi>will, importun'd Mr.</hi> M. <hi>to come from the Window and ſit by him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a private Conference with him, which laſted a conſiderable while;</hi> A. P. <hi>not being able to obtain of the</hi> Dr. <hi>a Proſecution of the Queſtion in debate, but called for a</hi> Bible, <hi>which when he would have opened, (I know not on what occaſion)</hi> A. P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> it was the Queſtion in hand to prove that Book to be the Word of God; <hi>Then he called for a</hi> Greek <hi>Teſtament, and asked</hi> A. P. <hi>if</hi> he at leaſt would allow of the <hi>Greek</hi> Edition? A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> he allow'd of it, but from his hands could receive neither the one nor the other, unleſs he made it out better than he had done yet, that it was the Pure Word of God. <hi>The ſtanders by ſeeing</hi> A. P. <hi>reject the</hi> Greek Teſtament, <hi>gave a little ſhout, as tho' he underſtood it not; but</hi> A. P. <hi>would have ſhewn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ſufficient Maſter of the Language, had he not been reſolv'd to give no occaſion of diverting the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe from the main Point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Continuing therefore to urge the</hi> Dr. <hi>for a poſitive Anſwer, he ſaid in the end,</hi> This Diſcourſe, whereby he call'd the Authority of Holy Scripture in Queſtion, tended to <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> A. P. <hi>granted his Poſition, and ſaid</hi> it was true, in their Principles, who having taken all Infallible Authority from the Church, there remain'd none for Holy Writ, which was left to each Man's fancy to receive, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or interpret at diſcretion; <hi>and urged the</hi> Dr. <hi>very preſſingly,</hi> to aſſign One Body of Chriſtians, which either had held poſitively or negatively, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29726:8"/> the Church of <hi>England</hi> does: <hi>And ſaid moreover,</hi> That if the Church of <hi>England</hi> were the True Church, ſhe muſt derive her Succeſſion from the Apoſtles; <hi>to that the</hi> Dr. <hi>Anſwer'd,</hi> He muſt have a Library of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> worth of Books to ſhew it. A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> he believ'd it, <hi>and added,</hi> That had he 100000 <hi>l.</hi> worth, he wou'd never make it out. <hi>Here the Gentleman mentioned above, in the ſecond place putting his hand into his Pocket, and taking out a little Volume, ſaid,</hi> he would ſhew the Succeſſion of the <hi>Roman Catholick Church</hi> at a much eaſier rate.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Here</hi> A. P. <hi>was over-ſeen, in letting the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſlip to a new Question upon the occaſion of the</hi> Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Where the</hi> Dr. <hi>deny'd, that St.</hi> Peter <hi>had ever been had</hi> Rome; <hi>to which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> himſelf, upon account of the general Tradition thereof, granted, that <hi>Peter</hi> had been put to Death at <hi>Rome,</hi> tho' he allow'd not of his ſitting there 25 years; <hi>And although</hi> A. P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> it was nothing neceſſary for the Truth of our Succeſſion, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould have reſided rather at <hi>Rome</hi> than <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch:</hi> If the <hi>Dr.</hi> pleas'd, he would make out to him, how, according to true Chronology, he might have reſided there 25 years, <hi>and produced his</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks <hi>relating to that Subject, and asked the Dr.</hi> who had Planted the Chriſtian Faith at <hi>Rome,</hi> of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in the Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans?</hi> whereas it is certain, St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet been there; nor any other Apoſtle, except <hi>St.</hi> Peter. <hi>But the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſeeing</hi> A. P. <hi>forward to prove the Point, paſsed to the Queſtion of</hi> Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, <hi>and the</hi> Real Preſence.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29726:8"/>14. A. P. <hi>ſeeing there was no Anſwer to be got to the main Queſtion, that he might not ſeem to decline a particular</hi> Controverſy, <hi>though he ſaid,</hi> That was far from the purpoſe intended, yet he would yield to the <hi>Dr.</hi> and accept thereof. <hi>Conſequently to which he demanded, who the Dr.</hi> would be Judged by in this matter? <hi>He anſwer'd,</hi> by the Univerſal Church. A. P. <hi>demanded,</hi> whether by the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church now extant, or that of the Four Firſt Centuries? If that of the Church now in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he had at leaſt Five to One againſt him; <hi>but he reply'd,</hi> That his Appeal was to the Four Firſt Centuries; <hi>Then</hi> A. P. <hi>deſired all preſent to take notice,</hi> that the <hi>Dr.</hi> would be Judged by the Teſtimonies of the Four Firſt Centuries.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Here mention was made (I know not on what occaſion) of the</hi> Council <hi>of</hi> Lateran, <hi>relating to the</hi> Real Preſence, <hi>when the</hi> Dr. <hi>asked abruptly,</hi> what Pope had preſided at that Council? which not occurring <hi>to</hi> A. P. <hi>the</hi> Dr. <hi>was pleaſed to ſay,</hi> he ſaw <hi>A. P.</hi> was a Man of no Reading; <hi>to which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> The <hi>Dr.</hi> was under a miſtake, that he had Read all the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, and had Volumes of Notes relating thereunto. <hi>He added moreover,</hi> That it imported nothing who it was preſided; that it was the great Council of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> where were Aſſembled near a Thouſand <hi>Biſhops, Prelates</hi> and <hi>Abbots;</hi> beſides a very great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Divines,</hi> the <hi>Legates</hi> of the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Jeruſalem, Cyprus;</hi> to ſay nothing of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes. <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>miſtaken much more groſly than</hi> A. P. <hi>in Point of Hiſtory, deny'd,</hi> That there were any from <hi>England,</hi> or that the Four Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs were there ſo much as by their <hi>Legates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29726:9"/>16. <hi>Here</hi> A. P. <hi>perceiving the</hi> Dr. <hi>to begin to wander from the Queſtion as it had been ſtated, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a Book which contained ſeveral Teſtimonies of Holy Fathers, as alſo a Paper in</hi> Engliſh <hi>for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the ſtanders by; having moreover ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book in his Pocket relating thereunto: Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>complain'd,</hi> he had hard meaſure, that he was come unprovided; <hi>and excepting againſt Authorities cited out of Authors not at hand, ſaid,</hi> let us take a Coach and go to a Library, A. P. <hi>anſwered,</hi> he was content: <hi>But not to diſappoint the Company,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired he would be pleaſed to hear the Quotations he had (as he believed) very exactly Quoted; <hi>and asking of the Dr.</hi> whom he would be pleaſed to hear firſt, naming ſeveral; <hi>The</hi> Dr. deſired to hear <hi>St.</hi> Ambroſe; <hi>whereupon</hi> A. P. <hi>read one of his</hi> 4th. <hi>Book</hi> 4th. <hi>Chap.</hi> De Sacramentis: tu forte dicis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Panis eſt uſitatus: Sed Panis iſte, Panis eſt ante Verba Sacramentorum, ubi acceſſerit Conſecratio, ex Pane fit Caro Chriſti. Hoc igitur aſtruamus. Quomodo poteſt qui Panis eſt, Corpus eſſe Chriſti? Conſecratione. <hi>Which for the ſatisfaction of the Hearers,</hi> A. P. <hi>read ſo in</hi> Engliſh. You ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance mine is uſual Bread: But that Bread, is Bread before the Words of the Sacraments, but the Words of Conſecration being pronounced, of Bread it becomes the Fleſh of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>as tho' be had gain'd a great Victory, calling for Pen and Ink, made ſome</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks <hi>upon the Authority Quoted; and then urged</hi> A. P. <hi>to ſet his hand to it.</hi> A. P. <hi>deſired the Dr.</hi> to have a little patience, and promiſed that when the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſhould have heard his whole Evidence, he would Sign it: <hi>But the</hi> Dr. <hi>reply'd,</hi> he would hear
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29726:9"/> no more, that <hi>A. P.</hi> was a Falſifier, that he who would quote one falſe Text, ought not to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited in another, A. P. <hi>anſwered,</hi> It would be no eaſie matter to prove that the Work quoted, was not of St. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> But if the <hi>Dr.</hi> doubted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he was content to lay no ſtreſs upon that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and deſired him to hear another of the ſame Author, to the very ſame intent, out of an unqueſtionable Work: <hi>But he abſolutely refuſed to hear any more, and importuned</hi> A. P. <hi>by himſelf and ſome Women preſent, to Subſcribe; ſo that</hi> A. P. <hi>for the ſpace of three quarters of an hour, could not obtain the favour of being heard in order to his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evidence, while the</hi> Dr. <hi>rambled through ſeveral impertinent Diſcourſes; and amongſt other things, falling upon</hi> Luther <hi>recounted I know not what Story of ſome Prieſt at</hi> Rome, <hi>who</hi> pronouncing the words of Conſecation, <hi>was heard to ſay,</hi> Bread thou art, and Bread thou ſhalt be; Wine thou art, <hi>&amp;c. and offering at another long paſſage out of</hi> Luther's <hi>Books,</hi> A. P. <hi>deſired the</hi> Dr. <hi>not to trifle away the time with idle Stories, ſaying,</hi> That little credit was to be given to <hi>Luther,</hi> who in his own Works, had left written many Dialogues which he had with the Devil; and acknowledgeth, that he left off ſaying of <hi>Maſs,</hi> purely upon the Devils perſuaſion: <hi>And then</hi> A. P. <hi>urged,</hi> that it was not likely if <hi>Luther</hi> had been of a falſe Belief, the Devil would be zealous to put him into a true One, being the Father of Lyes.</p>
            <p n="18">18. A. P. <hi>labour'd in vain to reduce the</hi> Dr. <hi>from his rambling Diſcourſes, and preſs'd that he might go on in citing his Authorities, offering at leaſt</hi> 20 <hi>times to read one out of</hi> Juſtinus, <hi>in his Apology to</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29726:10"/> Antoninus Pius, <hi>which the</hi> Dr. <hi>being ſomewhat ſpent with perpetual talking, was oblig'd to hear as follows,</hi> That Food over which Thanks are given by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in his own, <hi>(to wit)</hi> Chriſt's words, and whereby our Blood and Fleſh are by a change nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, is the Fleſh and Blood of the Incarnate JESUS. To <hi>which the</hi> Dr. <hi>Anſwer'd,</hi> That Text made nothing for Tranſubſtantiation. A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> It did at leaſt for the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> and he would produce other places, which alſo ſhould prove Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>ſaid,</hi> he believ'd the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> that is, (reply'd <hi>A. P.</hi>) you believe the Body and Blood of our Bleſſed Saviour, to be truly and really in the Sacrament of the Altar: <hi>To which the</hi> Dr. <hi>anſwered,</hi> he would not declare what he held in that matter; <hi>And thence forward would never be induced to hear a title more relating to a further proof of the matter in debate. But preſs'd ever and anon</hi> A. P. <hi>to ſubſcribe.</hi> A. P. <hi>being in a little heat at ſo unreaſonable proceedings, ſtruck the Table with his hand (as on the like occaſions he had done twice before) ſaying,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> believ'd cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he had a Fool to deal with; <hi>the</hi> Dr. <hi>reply'd,</hi> he would not come under his Ferula, <hi>to which</hi> A. P. <hi>anſwered,</hi> it was uſual to him in Schools to knock the Pulpit, though he had never given Ferula in his life: <hi>Then he offer'd to read a Text of St.</hi> Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>making for</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>but the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſaid,</hi> he had heard enough, <hi>and the Miſtreſs of the Houſe offering</hi> A. P. <hi>the</hi> Dr's. <hi>Paper, preſs'd him to Sign it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this occaſion</hi> A. P. <hi>inſtanced as follows,</hi> Should I <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> preſent my ſelf at a publick Court of Juſtice, and having 30 Witneſſes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; the firſt of which being heard, and ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29726:10"/> exceptions taken (though perhaps unreaſonably) at his Evidence: Would not that be an unequitable Judge, who on that occaſion ſhould refuſe to hear any more; and ſumming up that ſingle Evidence, ſhould require it ſhould be ſign'd: <hi>To which the Doctor anſwered, that</hi> A. P. knew well enough ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile's had little force to prove any thing; A. P. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd,</hi> The <hi>Dr.</hi> had us'd many, much leſs pertinent, altho' this was not ſo much a ſimile, as his very Caſe, The Holy Fathers being his Witneſſes: <hi>And preſently after the</hi> Dr. <hi>giving a reaſon, why he would hear no more, made the following compariſon very improperly,</hi> Should one <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> come to pay me 20 <hi>l.</hi> and the firſt half Crown which he told out, prove naught, I would ſuſpect all the reſt. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr.</hi> M. <hi>told the</hi> Dr. He would make uſe of his own ſimilitude, and therefore ask'd him; Whether if one coming to pay him ſuch a ſum, and he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking one of the half Crowns, he would refuſe to receive the Money, though the pay-Maſter ſhould offer another piece inſtead of that which he diſlik'd.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>Here the</hi> Dr. <hi>forgetful that he had appeal'd to the Holy Fathers, ſaid,</hi> He did not much value what they ſaid, and that many of them had fallen into ſeveral Errours in other matters, and why not in this. <hi>To which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That altho' one or two might have err'd in their private judgments, yet that in which all, or at leaſt much the greater part unanimouſly agreed, had ever been eſteem'd the Sentiment of the whole Church. <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>having Scripture in his hand, and</hi> A. P. <hi>having on ſome paſt occaſion cited that of our Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> He that hears not the Church, let him be unto you as a Heathen and a Publican: <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>ask'd</hi> A. P. What
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29726:11"/> Verſe that was; A. P. <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> That was not to the purpoſe, if the <hi>Dr.</hi> allow'd it to be true Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore; and deſir'd the <hi>Dr.</hi> to tell him where it was, but he did not; <hi>At laſt turning from place to place, he found it, and then endeavour'd to ſhew how that Text related to a private debate, and had no relation to any matter of Faith: Here</hi> A. P. <hi>complain'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that all this was impertinent to the queſtion in debate, although he ſaid,</hi> It was uſual on particular occaſions to make a general Law.</p>
            <p n="21">21. — <hi>Here the Gentleman mention'd above in the ſecond place,</hi> Deſir'd he might ſay ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the ſaid Text; <hi>But</hi> A. P. <hi>deſir'd the</hi> Dr. <hi>might have no occaſion of complaining there were more than one to encounter with him: Though on the</hi> Dr.<hi>'s ſide, the Schoolmaſter mention'd above, was conſtantly throwing in ſome</hi> Quaerie <hi>or other, either to divert</hi> A. P. <hi>or to entertain the Hearers: But as</hi> A. P. <hi>took little notice of what he ſaid there, ſo he has not much concern'd himſelf to relate here what he there imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently inſinuated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Here the Company breaking into different Parties, and</hi> A. P. <hi>ſeeing no ſatisfaction could be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to any thing he had propos'd, the</hi> Dr. <hi>nothing at all provok'd thereto, ſaid,</hi> He wonder'd any body would intruſt their Children with him; for <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> if he tampers with thoſe who are not his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, what would he do with ſuch as were under his care: <hi>To which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> He had engag'd his Promiſe for the one, and not for the other: <hi>On this occaſion the</hi> Dr. <hi>ſaid,</hi> There was no Credit to be given to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> being by there Principles breakers of there Words: <hi>At which Mr.</hi> M. <hi>taking exceptions, ſaid,</hi> He would remain no longer, where
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29726:11"/> ſuch Scandalous propoſitions were vented, upon which retiring out of the Room: A. P. <hi>deſir'd to know,</hi> Upon what ground the <hi>Dr.</hi> laid ſo injurious a Charge upon <hi>Roman Catholicks: The</hi> Dr. <hi>in place of excuſing what Paſſion might have made him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily aſsert, prov'd it againſt</hi> A. P. <hi>as follows,</hi> You believe yours to be <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> the only ſaving Church; but you are bound to ſave all you can: Therefore you are bound to break your Word given in your <hi>Paper,</hi> of not tampering with your Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars about Religion: A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> The ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium would prove as much againſt His Majeſty, as againſt A. P. <hi>which ſo he made out.</hi> His Majeſty belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved His to be the only ſaving Church: But His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty being Head of His People as much, and more than <hi>A. P.</hi> of his School, was bound to endeavour their Salvation as much or more then <hi>A. P.</hi> of his Schollars: Therefore His Majeſty was bound to break His Royal Word given to His People, of not forcing their Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>The</hi> Dr. <hi>was offended at</hi> A. P.'s <hi>Retortion, and call'd out for Witneſſes, ſaying,</hi> He had ſaid no ſuch thing, <hi>And the ſtanders by disturb'd thereupon, ſaid, A. P.</hi> was come to entrap the <hi>Dr.</hi> and inform againſt him: A. P. <hi>return'd,</hi> That he had no ſuch deſign, and believ'd that the <hi>Dr.</hi> had likewiſe no ſuch reflection when he ſpoke; <hi>but added withall,</hi> That he had done very ill to utter a Propoſition whence flowed naturally and unavoidably ſuch bad inferences. <hi>Then he deſir'd the</hi> Dr., To name the Schollar that ſhould prove <hi>A. P.</hi> either to have open'd his mouth in School-time of any controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted point; or tamperd with him out of School; <hi>adding,</hi> That the <hi>Dr.</hi> was much miſtaken in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29726:12"/> 
               <hi>Papiſts</hi> Principles, who unanimouſly taught with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That evil was not to be done, that good might come of it: <hi>And</hi> A. P. <hi>ſaid,</hi> He ought not to tell a lye, though the Converſion of the World depended upon it: <hi>After which he anſwered directly to the</hi> Dr.<hi>'s falſe Medium,</hi> viz. That no one was bound to do all the good preciſely poſſible (<hi>if ſo the</hi> Dr. <hi>might be oblig'd to give all he had to the Poor, and go to Preach the Faith to the</hi> Indians) and that it was a very good action to teach Learning <hi>Gratis</hi> with the fear of God; although one medled not with Religion.</p>
            <p n="24">24. A. P. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling to ſtay where Diſputes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to Calumniating, complain'd how he,</hi> Had had no ſatisfactory Anſwer to any thing that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd: And therefore deſir'd the favour, that the <hi>Dr.</hi> would give a ſecond Meeting, with an <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuenſis</hi> and Witneſs in ſome fair Library: <hi>To which the</hi> Dr. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That he was a man of much buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and had other Affairs in hand: But if <hi>A. P.</hi> for his private ſatisfaction would meet him in his own Library, he was content.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>The crowd being great, and the Room full of noiſe and diſorder,</hi> A.P. deſiring again a ſecond meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as above, <hi>began to withdraw; but the Maſter of the Houſe told him,</hi> If he would ſtep into the next Room, he would diſmiſs the People, and that Mr. <hi>M.</hi> had repair'd thither: <hi>To which he aſſented, but the</hi> Dr. <hi>as ſoon as he came in, began a long Parley with Mr.</hi> M. <hi>So that</hi> A. P. <hi>had no more Diſcourſe with the</hi> Dr. <hi>except that the</hi> Dr. <hi>at parting told, I know not what</hi> Impertinent ſtory of Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> as I take it <hi>(to wit)</hi> that he had taught, that the Chriſtians eat the Sacred Body of Chriſt like Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29726:12"/> 
               <hi>To which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> He had only the <hi>Dr.</hi>'s word for it; and deſir'd to know what the <hi>Dr.</hi> meant by Collops, which could have but two acceptations <hi>(to wit)</hi> that they eat Chriſt's Body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an appearance of viſible Fleſh, or that they eat it divided into many pieces, neither of which he was ſure came into Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Head to teach.</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Then the</hi> Dr. <hi>fearing his general Propoſition,</hi> Of <hi>Papiſts</hi> being breakers of their Word, <hi>might prove of no good conſequence to him, he ſaid,</hi> He ſpoke it only of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> A. P. <hi>Then thanking him for his Complement, reply'd,</hi> It was not ſo, but that his Propoſition was general, as appears by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium he took to prove it, to wit, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> believ'd their's to be the only ſaving Religion; which was not a point of Doctrine peculiar to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> but common to the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> Church; there being no more true Religions than there are Gods. <hi>Then he told the</hi> Dr. He underſtood not the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Principles, neither ſhould he ever aſſign one different from thoſe of other <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>On this occaſion the</hi> Dr. <hi>had a fling at the</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Power: <hi>To which</hi> A. P. <hi>reply'd,</hi> That was ſo far from being a common Doctrine amongſt the Society, that it was expreſly forbid under moſt ſevere Cenſures, not only to treat of it in Schools, but even to ſpeak of it in familiar Diſcourſes: <hi>Then the</hi> Dr. <hi>cited</hi> Mariana <hi>and</hi> Suarez, <hi>and added,</hi> That <hi>Parſons</hi> had taught it in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time: <hi>To which</hi> A. P. <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> oblig'd not themſelves to follow any private Author's Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; <hi>and added,</hi> That whatever <hi>Parſons</hi> had judg'd in the Theory, it was the <hi>Reformers</hi> who had reduc'd it to practice; who had taken the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29726:13"/> priviledge upon a falſe pretence of Goſpel Liberty to ſpill more Chriſtian Blood, through all <hi>Germany, Bohemia, France, Low-Countries, Holland, England,</hi> and where-ever they aſſum'd the Reforming Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, than ever the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> had done from from Chriſt's time, nor ſhould he ever ſhew they propagated their Faith by the Swords Point: And ſince he by his odious Inſinuations had oblig'd <hi>A. P.</hi> to ſpeak the Truth: It was manifeſt from Hiſtory, that the pretended <hi>Reformers</hi> had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and endeavour'd to Depoſe more Princes in the ſpace of 150 years, than the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> had done in 1600. witneſs the King of <hi>Spain</hi> thrown out of his Poſſeſſions of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> witneſs <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> with his whole Race diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd of his Hereditary Kingdom of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;</hi> witneſs <hi>Charles</hi> the V. depriv'd of the Name of Emperour, and call'd <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Gant</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Haſs</hi> at the head of 100000 Men; witneſs the Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Geneva,</hi> without any Authority Depos'd, and the Government transfer'd to the People: <hi>He added,</hi> That our own Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> had imbrac'd the ſame Principles, as was manifeſt from the unjuſt Detainment and Behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Queen <hi>Mary Stuart: And he ſaid,</hi> He was unwilling to reflect on the Father of his moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty; that the <hi>Scotch Covenant:</hi> And late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Bills of Excluſion</hi> preſented in three Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were a ſufficient Argument what Spirit run along with the <hi>Reformation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo bidding the</hi> Dr. <hi>Good night,</hi> Deſir'd him to be more wary another time, how he objected things that muſt naturally oblige his Adverſary to ſo ſevere a Recrimination.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29726:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
